[Music]
w
hello and welcome everybody welcome to
this uh science astrophysics cosmology
Etc episode of the ask abijit show I'm
going to have a smaller audience today I
know that but that's perfectly all right
this is my favorite topic this is the
topic essentially so I hope you're all
doing great and uh welcome to everybody
let's see who all is there in the live
chat right now I can see Tommy verti
Yash tiari anit Mishra Tad Brown anurag
J Joy deep feminist
Slayer Om biger hello gay molic
geopolitical du sonel Kumari paml nandi
Mikel random skull viand RI Anita kup uh
jippy
Phoenix uh anit
shetti Kanan danaj pulkit grower sual Ms
Amit Samar Priyanka javala anurag J
nikil Xander torto utar Zin Jay guman K
viand RI m m vant Kar Falcon anit chti
Zub isong chard Kari Brian Lord aush s
Sharma new wise 45 King Gully vishaka
kabila um and who else miir PRN g o
usop jatin Singh and many many other
people so welcome to all of you I will
not greet all of you individually
because it's not possible to do that but
thank you so much for being here so uh
this is going to be a session in which
I'm going to take questions that you
have asked in the comments and this is
going to be kind of a different session
I'm going to take 10 to 15 questions
maximum because we're doing this much
more frequently so I'm going to take the
best questions that you have asked thus
far I've been doing in the past year or
so I don't know 30 40 questions I'm
taking I think we're going to cut down
on that I'll take 10 to 15 questions at
most your best questions so if you want
me to answer your questions ask ask the
best possible questions you can and what
do I mean by the best questions it means
questions that will benefit everybody
questions who's answers will benefit as
many people as possible so ask your best
questions so I'm going to take 10 to 15
questions from the comments and then I'm
going to take maybe five questions from
the live chat when the show is winding
down all right so that's how I'm going
to play this today so let us go into the
questions what questions do we have
today what mix of questions do we have
here we go AAL Chan says why does
inflation 10us 36 seconds after the big
bang still have a high uncertainty even
after Cosmic microwave background
radiation Imaging also is there Eternal
inflation not just at the Big Bang all
right so what is inflation what is this
Cosmic cosmological inflation and does
it not work I mean does it have a high
uncertainty I'm assuming what he's
asking by high what he means by high
uncertainty is that we don't have
evidence of that is that so so it's a
long answer
uh so let's uh so let's take it step by
step first of all Cosmic inflation is
part of The Big Bang Theory but it was
not part of the initial Big Bang Theory
the initial Big Bang Theory uh was based
on a couple of uh rules a couple of
principles first of all that the rules
of general relativity are the is the
framework general relativity is the
framework set of rules that governs the
universe that was the first uh
consideration of The Big Bang Theory and
secondly The Big Bang Theory was was
about taking the data into account
whatever data we have we have data we
have observational evidence that the
galaxies are all receding they're all
moving away from us and they moving away
from us at speeds that are proportional
to their distance from us so the further
away the galaxies are the the faster
they are moving away from us so that's
the kind
of information that we had So based on
this what we what we what we saw is that
uh if you take these things into account
then certain uh certain logical
considerations come out of this so for
example as per general relativity if you
fill the universe with matter which we
know is there matter and energy light
and radiation and all that and if it is
reasonably evenly distributed as we know
it is at the largest scales then that
universe that you are constructing in
this manner it will not remain static
like the Fred Hy J narar Theory steady
state Theory it it won't remain static
it would it must either expand or it
must contract okay so it's either an
expanding universe or a Contracting
Universe based on this and we know it's
an expanding Universe based on
observational evidence and then what you
do is you go backwards in time you
extrapolate this backwards in time and
that was a big idea of the Big Bang The
Big Bang Theory so the Big Bang Theory
makes a number of predictions okay and
I'm not going to go into the details of
that but these predictions have been
verified and that's why the Big Bang
Theory what we call the Big Bang Theory
is the theory that works it is the best
theory that we have right now okay all
the other theories whichever they are
they kind of have faltered here or the
other but the Big Bang Theory works but
there are certain predictions of the
original Big Bang the that did that did
not
work for example look once the Big Bang
happens this alleged explosion It's
actually an expansion of the universe
but once this happens you have the
univer the various components and parts
of the universe that move apart from
each other
this happens over billions of years so
you have large areas of the universe
that have not been in contact with each
other for 13.8 billion years let's say
so therefore if you look in different
directions in the universe you should
see different temperatures different
parts of the universe at different
temperatures right logically makes sense
but it's not there it's All Uniform same
temperature everywhere why is that and
then as per the Big Bang there should be
the in the very early early uh uh part
of the universe the very early uh let's
say time period of the universe there
should have been the production of
exotic weird particles like magnetic
monopoles Etc well where are they we
have never discovered a single magnetic
monopole anywhere right and then the
universe should have spatial curvature
it should be curved but it's a flat
universe that we see what do I mean by a
flat universe you know the the flatness
problem why is the universe flat what do
I mean when I say that the universe is
flat see let's say you have a ball okay
a spherical object on a spherical object
if you take three points it should draw
a triangle right yes should do a draw
triang triangle now the geometry that we
learned in school it says that when you
have a triangle the sum of the three
angles is what
180° 180 I think it's 180 right but in
curved space it could be more than 180
or it could be less than 180 depending
on the curvature if it's positive or
negative curvature but what we what we
see is that it's it's essentially flat
space the universe is flat if you draw a
triangle three very far apart objects
you're going to see the sum of the
angles is 180 so you have a flat
universe there is no measurable
curvature so these are the problems with
the Big Bang Theory and that's where
inflation comes in so inflation was
proposed by Alan G in 1979 1980 I think
the paper came out in 1981 but it was
proposed that the idea popped into his
head uh in
1979 okay so
inflation is what solves these problems
so inflation is this state of the
universe that is before well it's a very
very initial part of the of the Big Bang
uh essentially before the Big Bang you
could say so you have a very early
universe and then there's inflation and
that's kind of the big bag so in this
inflationary state of the universe the
dominant form of energy according to
this Theory wasn't matter it wasn't
radiation it wasn't all of that it was
the dominant energy was inherent to the
fabric of space
itself okay space itself was full of
energy and it had a tremendously high
energy density okay and this incredibly
high energy density that was inherent to
the fabric of space itself that is what
caused the universe to expand rapidly
and it was not just rapid expansion it
was super luminal expansion the the
fabric of space or space time expanded
faster than the speed of Life Light
itself so you can break the speed of
light if it is spacetime itself that
expands so that can expand at any speed
that was the thing super luminal
expansion okay and so this caused the
universe to expand r ridiculously
rapidly super Lumin super luminally
rapidly and this caused the universe to
be stretched so large that it
essentially became indis
indistinguishable from
flatness okay and because it expanded so
rapidly and so on so that's why if you
look at the universe in different
directions if you look at various parts
of the
universe then we will see the same
properties everywhere uniform properties
of the universe everywhere because they
all originated in a from a previously
connected state in the very beginning
okay and also when inflation ends okay
inflation is not something that goes in
forever it ends at some point in time
and it did end so when this ended all
this energy that was inherent that was
part of the fabric of space it
transformed into matter and antimatter
and radiation and whatnot and this in
and by this process we also avoid the
production of exotic particles magnetic
monopoles Etc but magnetic monopoles
could still exist but it's just that we
have not found them maybe they are
stretch they they are spaced very very
far apart and so on so that is inflation
it solved the problems of uh of the big
Bank of the original Theory so it is
kind of an addendum to The Big Bang
Theory it is something that we attached
on top of the Big Bang Theory but yeah
it it it makes predictions that many of
these predictions have have been uh
verified so Quantum fluctuations for
example it says says that Quantum
fluctuations during inflation Quantum
fluctuations is it comes out of quantum
field Theory uh you can kind of violate
certain V violate the Heisenberg un
uncertainty principle as long as you do
it within a certain time time frame and
so on so Quantum fluctuations during
this period of inflation would produce
the seeds of density fluctuation so you
have if you if you look at the universe
of the largest scales it's kind of
homogeneous isotropic and all that but
if you look at it at smaller more local
scales you have you know fluctuations of
density you have galaxies and clusters
of galaxies in some places and some
places you have voids there's nothing in
there except for maybe interstellar
medium protons and electrons and all
that so why is it that why is it like
that it's because that it's because of
the fact that the quantum fluctuations
in the very early Universe during the
inflationary phase they produced the
seeds of today's density fluctuations so
all of those over densities they also
have produced micro black holes and all
but that's a different story so those
fluctuations Quantum fluctuations in the
very early phase during inflation they
eventually gave rise to all these all
these regions of high and low density
and galaxies and all this all the
structure that we have in the universe
okay and one of the predictions of
inflation is that the Universe should
should be filled
with we know we have Cosmic microwave
background radiation
cmbr we have the CMB Cosmic microwave
background which is the background of
the electromagnetic waves it's light
it's photons similarly there should be a
cosmic gravitational wave background
primordial gravitational waves should be
all around us the universe should be
filled with these primordial
gravitational waves and these primordial
gravitational waves should actually
imprint themselves on the cosmic
microwave background as something that's
called B modes and there was a false
positive detection of this the bicep 2
experiment yeah there was a famous video
there on YouTube and so all so that's
not yet been proven but a number of
things have been proven and obviously
flatness it should the universe should
be almost nearly flat but not quite
perfectly flat and little bit of that
could be there so that is what inflation
is so it is not something that is a high
uncertainty lots of evidence of
inflation has has been found it it
solves the problems of the original Big
Bang Theory it it improves it
significantly right uh so that's what it
is eternal inflation not just a big bang
well in that we have to go into delve
into different theories maybe there is
inflation that goes on even eternally
and so on but overall the the point is
inflation is the best theory that we
have if we attach it on top of the Big
Bang Theory it it essentially accounts
for the the state of the universe the
way we see it today all right okay next
question pranav hariharan says what is
the cosmic Dawn and Epoch of
reionization in cosmology the cosmic
Dawn so the cosmic Dawn is it it refers
to this period in the early Universe now
we are no longer in the inflationary
period but we still in the early
Universe phase so the cosmic Dawn is
that period of the universe its history
when the first stars and the first
galaxies began to form and they began to
light up the cosmos it's a very early
universe okay so before this Cosmic Dawn
when the first stars and galaxies began
to light up the universe there was
something called The Cosmic Dark Ages
the dark ages of of the universe and
this was a
time after the first Cosmic microwave
background ration the CMB was emitted of
this the first CMB the first light was
emitted about 380,000 years roughly
after the big bang okay so the first CMB
the first Cosmic microwave background
The Relic the Afterglow of the Big Bang
is emitted about 380,000 years after the
big
bang and that is the end of the dark
ages of the universe now what are the
features of the cosmic Dawn so you have
the formation of the very first Stars
okay uh these are the these are called
the first generation stars or population
three stars and these are composed
almost entirely of hydrogen and helium
as the heavier elements had not yet been
formed see all the heavy elements that
we uh know of we have blood in our veins
what is in the blood what makes the
blood red hemoglobin what is the thing
that makes hemoglobin red it is
iron okay iron is a heavy element now
iron how is iron formed iron is formed
when stars die when a star starts
producing iron through Fusion that is
the death nail of a star because no
matter how power large and big and all
that a star is it simply can't fuse iron
and that is iron is like it's like
poison for a star the moment it starts
producing iron it's life is measured in
milliseconds uh so iron comes from Stars
calcium oxygen nitrogen everything
comes is all these elements they formed
inside stars but when we talking about
the first stars of the universe and the
cosmic Dawn the population three stars
then it was all hydrogen and helium
because hydrogen fuses to form helium
and that's how the first light came out
okay I mean the first Stars lit up so
these are the very early stars that were
part of the uh Cosmic Dawn and these
were very massive stars we we believe
these were very massive stars and they
were very shortlived stars and then the
light from these first Stars it began to
ionize the surrounding neutral hydrogen
so at this time there was hydrogen
everywhere neutral hydrogen not ionized
Hydro hydrogen it was neutral hydrogen
so the light from these first Stars
began to ionize this neutral hydrogen
what do I mean by ionizing hydrogen it
means break the hydrogen atoms apart and
what what comes out a hydrogen atom the
standard hydrogen atom not the heavier
Isotopes the standard hydrogen atom
proteum has one proton and one electron
and that's it no neutrons so when you
ionize that you essentially get a free a
free proton and a free electon
okay so the light from these first Stars
began to ionize the surrounding neutral
hydrogen and this was the transition
from the Dark Ages to a universe filled
with light and then with the first Stars
eventually after a while you have the
formation of the first Galaxy the first
Proto galaxies and these would have been
initially pretty small and they are
formed from the gravitational collapse
of gas and dark dark matter was
obviously there yes Dark Matter well
yeah dark matter as well so overall this
is what leads to the formation of larger
structures over time okay so that is the
cosmic Dawn the other question is what
is
reionization so reionization is this
period in which the predominantly
neutral hydrogen in the universe was
replaced it was reionized by the first
luminous sources which is the first
stars that we just spoke about the first
Stars their light re it ionizes the the
predominantly neutral hydrogen in the
universe so this is something that comes
directly after the cosmic Dawn because
until this light comes from the first
Stars the hydrogen will remain neutral
okay so this is what reionization is the
the epoch of reionization it immediately
followed the cosmic Dawn and this com
fundamentally changed the state the
nature of the universe okay so the first
stars form and it is the higher
frequency
photons from these stars that are
capable of ionizing hydrogen because see
it's it's light the stars are giving off
light if you have a sunik star let's say
you have white light predominantly but
you have light in other frequencies as
well and it is the higher frequency
light the more energetic photons that
are capable of actually dislodging an
electron from a hydrogen atom okay so it
is the ultraviolet Right light the
energetic the high more energetic light
from these Stars split the hydrogen
atoms and ionize them and this gradually
made the universe transparent it was
before that it was opaque and you had
bubbles of ionized hydrogen that formed
around the first stars and the first
galaxies and these bubbles eventually
overlapped which gave rise to an ionized
Intergalactic medium if you look at
space today it's full of it's it's
almost a vacuum and you have Cosmic
microwave background radiation in there
2 point something Kelvin but you also
have
ionized hydrogen which is protons and
neutrons you know lying around so that
is that all originated from that time
okay so when did reionization begin the
exact timing is kind of unknown but it's
between half a billion and one billion
years after the big bang and it was most
likely a gradual process starting with
the with
uh with isolated regions of ionized
hydrogen and eventually over time
processing progressing into a un
Universe wide reionization so it's a
gradual process maybe half a billion
years after the big bang maybe a billion
years and maybe the whole process took
half a billion or a billion years so
that is the the cosmic Dawn and that is
the epoch of reionization in cosmology
it helps us understand how the first
stars and galaxies and black holes also
formed how the all of these
structures how all of that formed
structures larger structures like uh
Galaxy IES like like clusters of
galaxies and then obviously at the
largest scales largest scales you have
these filamentary structures that are
mediated by dark matter and which we can
kind of you know we can deduce their
their existence through gravitational
lensing and all that so all of that you
know so that's why it's important to to
it is key to understanding How the
Universe evolve and it helps us
understand the timeline the history of
the universe and the interstellar medium
also helps understand uh you know the
formation of galaxies the prop
propagation of light and all that so
yeah that is the cosmic Dawn and that's
the epoch of reionization in
cosmology next question is by Akash
Buller so in case you people I mean many
of you um must be more recent
subscribers but when I started the asket
show in the very beginning I think in
the year 2021 Akash used to ask a lot of
questions very good questions I used to
take a lot of his lot of his questions
it of upset lots of people that I took
so many questions from Akash but he
asked so many brilliant questions and he
was also one of the first people to
start putting out time stamps you know
so I I am very grateful and I'm I'm glad
to see Akash here again I I hope you're
doing well Akash So yeah thank you and I
hope you're doing great and let's have
more questions you always have great
questions so the question is under brain
cosmology how much do you think the ep e
pyrotic the e pyrotic Universe makes
sense is it supported by mathematics so
I essentially have to uh explain two
things here what is brain cosmology and
what is the e pyrotic universe so settle
down and let me tell you the story so
what's brain cosmology first of all
let's talk about brain cosmology so
brain cosmology is a theoretical
framework in theoretical physics that
extends the concept of extra Dimensions
so what are dimensions we know the three
dimensions length breadth height right
and we also speak about the fourth
dimension time so in general relativity
we have four dimensional space time okay
so these four dimensions are the
familiar dimensions for us so in brain
cosmology we extend this concept we
extend the the concept of Dimensions
Beyond The Familiar 3 +1 four
dimensional fabric that we kind of
understand and uh it could you can have
more Dimensions five Dimensions you
could have 10 Dimensions 11 Dimensions
26 dimens ions and so on so all this is
part of string theory and M Theory and
yeah main concept is more than four
dimension so brain cosmology so the key
concept here is a brain and obviously
they have bulk also let me explain what
is brain what is bulk so the term brain
is short for membrane so in this concept
you have multi-dimensional objects
within higher dimensional space let's
say you have five dimensional space or
you have 10 or 11 dimens space in that
you have a brain which is let's say
threedimensional
let's let's talk about two brains a two
two brain is a two-dimensional surface a
three brain is a
three-dimensional volume a four brain
brain would be a four-dimensional hyper
volume and so on within a much larger
thing called a
bulk okay so yeah so a brain is short
for a membrane it it is a
multi-dimensional object embedded within
a higher dimensional space or SpaceTime
okay so the observable universe in brain
cosmology is is typically thought of as
a three brain threedimensional brain
embedded in a higher higher dimensional
hyper surface or hyper volume which is
called the
bulk and where are these extra
Dimensions you say so these extra
Dimensions could be compactified such
that we cannot observe them or they
could be large also but for some reason
don't observe them but the the main the
more popular way of looking at it is is
that these dimensions are so small so
tiny so curled up and compactified that
it's not possible for us to observe them
but their effects uh are very much
significant okay and the bulk is this
higher dimensional hyper surface hyper
volume whatever hyper volume hyper space
whatever you want to call it within
which brains exist so that is the bulk
so brains live inside the bulk bu and
the bulk can have its own properties it
can have its own Dynamics its own rules
and all of these obviously will
influence the brains so now let's talk
about forces we know that we have these
forces in the universe we can think of
we can how many forces do we have four
right what do we have electromagnetism
gravitation the weak force and the
strong force the four forces that we
know of now um one of the interesting
things in brain cosmology is how these
forces operate so in brain cosmology the
standard for Force like electromagnetism
the strong force the weak Force these
three forces they are they operate on
the brain only they confined to the
brain whereas gravity
propagates into the
bulk okay so let me repeat that
electromagnetism the strong nuclear
force and the weak nuclear force are
confined to the brain only to the three
dimensions that we are familiar with but
gravity propagates into the bulk which
means it operates on all the dimensions
let's say you have five dimensional
hyper volume or whatever hyperspace or
you have 10 dimensional 11 dimensional
hypers hyper space then gravity operates
on all of those dimensions and that
explains why gravity is much weaker
compared to the other forces because it
leaks out into all these other
dimensions so that's how it this this
Theory brain world theory brain Theory
uh explains
why gravity is weak I mean that's the
that's the hierarchy problem why is
gravitation why is the force of gravity
exponentially weaker than the other
fundamental forces exponential is a weak
word that's how much weaker gravity is
compared to even the weak nuclear force
okay so that's called the hierarchy
problem and by allowing gravity to
spread across and and leak into all
these extra Dimensions it naturally
weakens its observable strength on the
three dimensions that we are familiar
familiar with okay so that is that kind
of explains the hierarchy problem and
then there are various models in brain
cosmology that Explain the origin and
evolution of the universe for so uh
there is a model called the Raman
sundaram and Le
um uh Lisa Randall and Raman sundaram
the Raman the the Randall sundram model
so according to the Randall sundram
model the universe that we live in is a
three brain because three dimensions
which lives inside of five dimensional
bulk and that kind of explains certain
cosmological
observations uh and brain Theory can
brain cosmology can provide explanations
for the Big Bang and Cosmic inflation
for example it it suggests that let's
say you have this hyper surface hyper
hyper space which contains multiple
brains
and this some models that suggest that
the Big Bang was actually a collision
between two brains okay
so the Big Bang was it actually
posits An Origin of the big bang and
what came before the Big Bang so you
have two brains and they Collide within
the hyperspace and this Collision
releases tremendous amounts of energy
which
causes the the effects that we are
familiar with as the big bag so if you
want to visualize brain cosmology you
can imagine a sheet of paper a sheet of
paper which which represents our
threedimensional universe a three brain
and this sheet is floating in space that
we are familiar with which is actually
the higher dimensional uh hyperspace the
bulk and there could be other sheets of
paper parallel to our or in other other
parts of the hyperspace and the bulk
itself the hyperspace could be gigantic
vast and complex beyond our imagination
okay so objects and forces on the sheet
of paper are are confined to the sheet
but gravity it leaks out and goes into
the hyperdimensional bul
uh that
is kind of how brain cosmology works now
what is the I pyrotic universe so the e
pyrotic universe is a cosmological model
that proposes an alternative to the
standard Big Bang Theory and it's it's
based on ideas of string theory and
brain cosmology so it suggests like I
said that the Universe was created not
from the Big Bang which happened for no
reason but it was the result of a
collision between two brains and the
word e pyrotic comes from Greek
pyrosis pyite okay it's something to do
with fire okay so what are the what are
the key concepts of the eotic inflation
universe so there was a brain Collision
okay the universe exists the universe
that we live in exists in a
three-dimensional brain the birth and
evolution of the universe were the
result of a collision between our brain
and a different brain another brain that
exists in this bulk and this Collision
released gigantic vast amounts of energy
which triggered the creation and
expansion of the universe okay so there
is a pre- big bang scenario in this okay
the so according to B big bang big bang
cosmology it all starts with a
singularity or something close to a
singularity but the expotic model it
says that there could there was a
pre-existing State and that's the
difference and it avoids certain well it
avoids the singularities and infinite
densities infinite curvature infinite
temperatures all that which come along
with the big bang cosmology right so
that is what the e pyrotic universe
thing is and uh thetic model also
suggest that the Universe could undergo
an endless cycle of these brain
collisions expansions even contractions
so let's say you have brains that
Collide
periodically right so it's kind of a
cyclic process so each Collision is a is
a new Big Bang then you have an
expansion then you have a cooling
even eventual contraction let's say and
then there's another Collision which
does the same thing again so yeah that's
the e pyrotic universe and you can
visualize it as two parallel sheets of
paper in a higher dimensional space and
they are moving towards each other and
they Collide and that initiates the big
bag now uh you asking about mathematics
right is this is thetic Universe
supported by mathematics so yes it's
obviously built on equations
mathematical equations derived from
General relativity from string theory
and brain Dynamics and these equations
describe how the brains evolve and how
they interact how they Collide within
higher dimensional
space and it uses uses various
modifications of the Einstein field
equations to incorporate the extra
dimensions and brain interactions and
all that uh so yeah so brain that's
brain cosmology and it needs to match
observational data and it it predicts
certain
effects it it predicts the the formation
of large scale structures like galaxies
and custs of galaxies through the growth
of initial density fluctuations which we
spoke about in the previous answer also
it predicts the presence of barion
acoustic oscillations which are regular
periodic fluctuations in the density of
bionic matter visible bionic matter
which is which is the all the matter
that that produces light in the universe
so it it it predicts the presence of
regular periodic fluctuations the
density of this visible bionic matter
and so on so it makes some predictions
some of which are actually bore out and
there are some large scale uh structure
surveys coming up for example the ukl
satellite went up into the L2 lrange
Point recently I think last year it's
going to start operating very soon if
it's not already operational and there
is a an observatory coming up in Chile
called the Vira Rubin Observatory so
data from all these experiments will be
used to SP will do will be used to test
more of these predictions of the E
pyrotic model and other models as well
about density fluctuations and higher
order statistics and and whatnot so uh
that is the long winded answer to this
question that's what brain cosmology is
that is what the eotic universe is that
is how it is supported definitely by
mathematics very robust very interesting
very complicated mathematics for sure
yeah it makes predictions that actually
can be Ed that can be falsified it's
falsifiable predictions so it's a good
model for sure and let's see how it is
borne out by upcoming experiments and uh
tests all right great
question okay indrajit says recently I
came across a paper about the
confirmation of gravitational wave
background existing in the fabric of
space India has also given its
contribution in the international
research by measuring millisecond Pulsar
in this experiment called pul are timing
array how does this all work as these
ultra low frequency gravitational waves
are hard to detect
okay uh I haven't seen a paper that
confirms the gravitational W back
background which would be it would be
startling if that happens and nobody
would be happier than me so what is this
gravitational wave background we are
quite familiar hopefully those of us who
are interested in physics with the
cosmic microwave background right which
is the uh the leftover light of the of
the Big Bang the cosmic Dawn right
that's what it is now what is the
gravitational wave background so the
early
Universe also produced gravitational
waves tremendous numbers of grav
tremendous amounts of gravitational
waves and that should also be there in
the background now what are the things
that can produce gravitational waves
first of all Cosmic infl and the things
that happen within Cosmic inflation that
obviously can produce gravitational
waves uh primordial black holes and
their interactions can produce
gravitational waves in today's Universe
the merger of black holes the merger of
neutron stars the mergers of neutron
stars and black holes and various such
cataclysmic events can produce
gravitational
waves um so you you will have and we
know the gravitational waves exists
these waves Exist by now we know that
the first detection was in 2015 if I'm
not mistaken by go so we know these
waves exist but right now the technology
that we have it is such that we can only
measure not waves but tsunamis I'm
talking about amplitudes see waves come
in various sizes right you've got tiny
Ripples and you got gigantic waves
tsunamis so right now we can only
observe gravitational wave
tsunamis but I assure you there's a
gravitational wave background out there
with with mediumsized waves small waves
and then then those tiny little ripples
in space time and when we start
detecting that those Ripples and those
smaller waves that's when we going to
end up having a new set of eyes that
will help us see the universe in a light
that we've never seen it's not light
it's it's gravitational waves so we are
familiar with the light right the light
that we are familiar with that is also
waves but it is electromagnetic waves
and similarly there are gravitation
waves and we don't have eyes that can
see gravitation radiation but those
waves do exist we know that so that is
what the gravitational wave background
is and it exists in the fabric of space
it's it's everywhere but we don't it's
too it's too faint because like we just
discussed the gravitational force is the
weakest of the force it is exponentially
hyper exponentially weaker than the
closest weak Force which is the weak uh
nuclear force and that's why these
ripples are so insanely hard to detect
essentially you would have to you would
need to have a detector the size of the
Milky Way to to detect some of these
effects and so on uh so that's what it
is so I haven't seen any evidence of the
of the confirmation of the gravitational
way background I know it's there we all
know it's there but the confirmation no
it's not happened as far as I know but I
will look it up I mean I know the
technology doesn't exist to confirm this
okay now the other question is about
millisecond pulsar and the Pulsar timing
array how does this work U ultra low
frequency gravitation waves are hard to
DET all gravitation waves are hard to
detect now what are millisecond pulsars
what are what is the this thing called
the Pulsar timing array first of all
what's a pulsar so a pulsar is a highly
magnetized neutron star what's a neutron
star a neutron star is a gigantic Atomic
nucleus just neutrons neutrons that's it
it's a gigantic Atomic nucleus it's well
it's the size of a small small town or
something but it is the mass of an
entire star essentially inside it and uh
I'll not go into the way these objects
are produced but yes you have neutron
stars now some of these neutron stars
are
extraordinarily highly
magnetized okay and this pin it a very
high rate and this magnetization of this
this property that it's highly
magnetized it ends up it ends up doing
something strange the neutron star emits
beams of high highly energetic radiation
electromagnetic radiation is light and
whatever other forms of radiation in
whichever frequencies x-rays gamma rays
whatever you want to call it yeah so
emits two beams of Highly energetic
radiation in opposite directions and it
it spins around around its axis very
rapidly so that's a
pulsar now what's a millisecond Pulsar a
millisecond Pulsar is a pulsar whose
period of rotation is less than 10
milliseconds okay less than 10
milliseconds so that's a millisecond
pulsar and we can detect pulsars on
Earth I mean some of them they their
beams of radiation are pointed towards
the Earth so we get these and and these
are extremely highly
periodic but at at a millisecond rate
okay you get that and it's extremely
well extr extremely precise the timing
is incredibly precise okay these
millisecond pulsars so now that's what a
millisecond Pulsar is now what's a
pulsar timing array so we have
millisecond pulsars we know a bunch of
known such pulsars and what we can do is
we can have an experiment in which we
detect an entire the Pulses from an
entire array of pulsars okay now what
that does is is that if there's a
gravitational wave that comes through
that passes by then there's going to be
a very tiny discrepancy in the timing
with which the pulse reaches you and if
this happens with multiple Pulsar at the
same time and we know how it is
correlated then we know that we have
detected a gravitational wave and based
on the U the anomaly based on the
discrepancy we can actually determine
the characteristics certain
characteristics of the gravitational
wave so that is the principle behind a
pulsar timing array and we have such
experiments out there at work thus far
they have not detected gravitational
waves thus far all right maybe because
our instrum in instrumentation number uh
the the the
accuracy with which we make these
detections isn't isn't strong enough
maybe it's not accurate enough so there
are reasons for this multiple reasons
that we can think of and very plausible
reasons but thus far we have not
detected gravitation waves using a
pulsar timing
array uh so that's what I know I'm not
sure about India's contribution in this
I've not read about that and I have not
read about the confirmation of a
gravitational W background but I hope I
have explained the concepts what is the
gravitation wave background I've
explained hopefully uh what is a pulsar
what's a neutron star what's a
millisecond pulsar and what's a pulsar
timing array and how does it uh how do
do such experiments hopefully in the
future detect gravitational waves so uh
yeah there you have
it okay pranav hariharan says in quantum
mechanics we start by reading about
matter waves or the de or Dei like we
like we say the dly hypothesis so my
doubt here is that what exactly is
oscillating in a matter wave yeah matter
waves right so what ex what is
oscillating in electromagnetic waves we
know that you have electric and magnetic
fields that are oscillating yeah that
way that way uh yeah so we in
electromagnetic in electromagnetic waves
electric and magnetic fields are
oscillating yes in gravitational waves
what is oscill so we're not talking
about gravitational waves here we're
talking about the the bo waves okay
matter waves we not don't let's not
confuse that with gravitational wav
that's a whole different thing in
gravitational waves it's SpaceTime
itself that is distorted but we are
talking about matter waves here so let's
let's talk about that so what is the Dei
hypothesis de brogi hypothesis which is
better known as wave particle duality it
is something Mr no Prince Lou Victor
whatever the Bo he was a prince he
proposed this as a massive breakthrough
in the 1920s it was a massive
breakthrough in quantum mechanics in
quantum physics at the time we did not
have mechanics yet it was a bunch of
jumbl disparate experiments and it was
very very confounding
until uh Mr Paul Dak came in and Mr
Heisenberg came in and hinger came in
and Pa all that okay I'll not go into
the history of this so so the the
hypothesis the the the brle hypothesis
is that particles like electrons Etc
have a wavelength what is this
wavelength it is h divid p where H is
the plank constant and P is the momentum
of the
electron okay and this wavelength of the
electron or whichever particle
fundamental particle subatomic particle
it's It's associated with the wav like
nature of the particle and then you have
the concept of the wave function so this
wav likee nature of the particle is
described by what we call a wave
function so that is the wave particle
duality partic particles
have a wave character a wave nature and
waves also have a particle character I
mean talk about the photon the photon is
a particle when we talk about the uh
when it comes to certain phenomena like
the photo electri effect you cannot
explain that unless you consider light
to be a particle a photon yes but when
it comes to other things like
uh uh like like the double slit
experiment Etc you have to think of
light as waves so there and that that
applies to electrons as well the same
wave particle duality so a partic so you
can have a partic everything has a
particle as well as as a wave nature
that's the wave particle duality now in
quantum mechanics the state of a
particle is described by what we call a
wave function s you know
s so what is this wave function this
wave function is a complex valued
function of space and time of x and t
and this wave function contains all the
information about that one particle so
that one particle let's say this
electron that we are referring to has a
wave function and this wave function is
a function of position and time space
and time x andt and it contains this
wave function contains all the
information about the particle and how
do we actually utilize it we we do we
take the square of the absolute value of
the wave function it's a complex valued
uh thing function so we take the square
of the absolute value of the wave
function and that gives us what it gives
us the probability density of finding
the particle at a position X at a time
T so so s this this wave function s is
not directly observable it has no real
physical meaning the square of its
absolute value has a physical meaning
and that is a probability density so
there was when the wave function first
came up okay when shinger came up with
the Shing equation there was this big
debate and everyone was perplexed as to
what does this s this function s
describe and schinger was of the opinion
that it describes the the distribution
of the electric of the of the charge of
the electron over space that was what he
believed initially until well there were
there was a revision of the
understanding of this so s itself the
wave function is not observable only the
the the the square of the absolute value
of the wave function it has a physical
meaning it is a probability density so
now the question is what is oscillating
right what exactly is oscillating in a
matter wave so it's not a physical
oscillation okay the the brly waves or
the show which are described by the wave
function s they are not they are not
like classical waves in a classical wave
in in a wave of water you have a
physical quantity like let's talk about
the light so you
have the electric field which oscillates
right or or in in sound waves you have
pressure that oscillates and and so on
but in matter waves it is the
probability amplitude that exhibits wav
likee behavor that's what it is so this
oscillation is is in the mathematical
sense of the complex phase it is not a
tangible physical quantity that we're
talking about okay so in a matter Wave
It's the complex phase of the wave
function that is oscillating and this
oscillation is not a physical movement
of matter but a variation in the
probability amplitude described by the
wave function and yeah you you if you
really want to understand this I mean
there's no intuitive way of looking at
it right because quantum mechanics is
completely non-intuitive it doesn't make
any sense whatsoever you just have to
get used to it you get used to these
ideas you cannot give metaphors and and
examples of the real world even though
the real world emerges from the quantum
World okay so that's what it is that is
what matter waves are that is what the
the brly it's not a hypothesis it's the
wave partical Duality and that's what it
means
okay feminist Slayer says what's why the
primary focus on reducing carbon dioxide
emissions when there are other potent
greenhouse gases like methane and
nitrogen oxides are there efforts to
reduce these other gases as well
additionally while promoting solar
energy to meet our energy needs how are
we addressing the issue of E-Waste
generated from solar technology lastly
does the extraction of fossil fuels and
minerals from Earth from the earth
increase the risk of natural disasters
such as earthquakes okay multiple
questions in one but it's a good
question yeah we talk about we talk
about reducing carbon dioxide emissions
there are other greenhouse gases poent
greenes like methane which is again
something that it's a hydrocarbon
methane is what CH4
chemistry I'm not I'm not that great
chemistry okay I think it's CH4 methane
okay it has carbon right and then you
have nitrogen oxides and all but the
major bulk of the greenhouse gases is
carbon based compounds like carbon
dioxide and methane and so on um yeah
but we talk about carbon dioxide how
much carbon dioxide because the bulk is
carbon dioxide are there efforts to
reduce these other gases as well I'm not
sure right now we focusing on carbon
dioxide because it is the biggest
problem that we have right uh so yeah
because carbon dioxide is the is the
major greenhouse gas and it is what what
is emitted let's say you burn coal what
comes out of it is carbon dioxide that
mostly comes out there are other gases
also that come out but the major gas
that comes out as a byproduct of burning
of coal is carbon dioxide once again
when you are
combusting petrol Gasol
kin which is aviation fuel or whatever
other hydrocarbon petrochemical thing
the major by product of this is carbon
dioxide so it makes sense to talk in
terms of carbon dioxide U yeah but of
course there are other greenhouse gases
when it comes to animal agriculture
there's the emission of methane which is
a big thing and so on but we focus on
carbon dioxide because it is the the
major component of the greenhouse gases
in the greenhouse effect um now talking
about solar energy to meet our energy
needs of course there's going to be
E-Waste generated from solar technology
so let's say you have a solar panel and
a solar panel has a certain lifespan
okay it's going to have a certain time
in which it is useful it has a certain
limited amount of utility let's say 5
years 10 years let's say hypothetically
okay after which it will no longer
generate the amount of power which that
you need so you're going to have to
dispose of it and get a new one right so
what happens to the thing that you
dispose the solar panel that you dispose
it's going to go into waste and it's
going to get hopefully recycled or it
just goes into a landfill or what I
don't know whatever happens so that is
the electronic waste the easte that uh
you're referring to over here and
obviously that's a problem but the deal
is this all human activity produces
waste you just can't do a thing about it
every biological activity produces waste
by the way I'm sure you're aware of
this and biological activity on a large
scale can transform formed the planet
what was the great oxygenation
catastrophe it was one of the first
Extinction events I mean before that the
before this thing happened you the Earth
was a very different place the
atmosphere was was very different there
was no oxygen it was for us a hellish
place a whole combination of Highly
noxious gases from our perspective and
then these microorganism organisms
evolved unicellular organisms that gave
out a tremendous amount of oxygenation
and this oxygen was a poison for all
other organisms and it K off most of
them there was the one of the first
Extinction events the great oxygenation
catastrophe and even today oxygen in
high concentration and all that is is
poisonous for even us so uh so
biological activity can produce waste
that can transform the planet in in a in
a let's say delerious fashion right so
there is that then you why do we have so
much iron rust you know Iron Ore where
does iron ore come from it comes from
bacterial activity again deep in the
earth's an Antiquity and when it comes
to human activity we need to extract
resources from the environment even
during the Stone Age we used Stones as
resources so we were because our
population was so low at the time it did
not have any real effect on the planet
but let's talk about a time about 5,000
years ago when we have the Saraswati
synu phase of the Indian history Indian
civilization in which the population of
of that that region north northern and
western India was about 5 million at
that time to sustain that population
obviously you would need to extract
resources from from the environment the
ecosystem the the the the ground you
would have to do Mining and also
obviously that will have some effect
obviously 5 million human being
population isn't great compared to what
it is today what 78 billion in India's
population is 1.4 billion now we're
talking about genuine Earth changing
consequences the point is
all human activity is going to create
waste it's going to affect the planet in
some way or the other and it's going to
change the
balance of the ecosystem of the
environment in some way or the other so
we do need transportation we do need
energy we do need all that all all has
to come from somewhere now ideally you
want to have a clean source of
energy so even if you want to have a
clean source of energy like like solar
energy you're going to need to to have
these solar panels and those solar
panels eventually will generate waste or
you could go for nuclear energy but then
it will produce nuclear waste which is
essentially just
thermal stuff which you can dispose of
safely but yeah that's that's a thing so
yeah there's nothing you can do about it
no matter how much you optimize the
technology and how how much you try to
reduce the the the impact on the planet
it's going to have an impact and the
last question is does the extraction of
fossil fuels and minerals from the earth
increase the risk of natural disasters
in Earth such as earthquakes well if you
have a reservoir of petroleum that you
completely empty it's going to cause a
void below the Earth's surface and that
can obviously cause the displacement of
of soil and rock and whatever and it it
can cause a minor localized earthquake
and more than that it's essentially it's
actually damning up of water that causes
natural disasters such as earthquakes if
you have a region that is of the planet
that is hilly lots of rivers and you Dam
up like 50 of those rivers in a
reasonably small area then that can
cause earthquakes and things like that
natural disasters or it can it can cause
flooding and so on so yeah it's not the
extraction of fossil fuels and minerals
from the Earth but it's damning up of
water of of of of of rivers Etc that has
a higher chance of causing earthquakes
so on but even the extraction of fossil
fuels petroleum you know uh raw raw
petroleum if you if you completely empty
out reservoirs then it can cause the
collapse of the reservoir because it
leaves a void behind and then it can
perhaps cause an earthquake so yeah
there we have
it okay swapnil says are there any non
living nonhuman are there any nonhuman
living organisms such as plants or
animals or insects of or microorganisms
that exhibit Suicidal Tendencies or
engage in self-destructive Behavior
leading to their own
death right there are cases in which
this happens it's more of who was it
altruistic suicide somebody said I
forget the name of the sociologist who
came up with altruistic suicide I am
sure some of us some of our viewers will
know who it was anyway so let's talk
about a colony of ants
a colony of ants when it comes under
attack by a predator let's say a wasp or
a Hornet or something then in certain
species of ant the ants can the worker
ants can
self-destruct and and release some
sticky chemicals or some some noxious
chemicals that ward off the the attacker
the Predator so they do it they they
destroy their body and die essentially
commit suicide side for an altruistic
purpose to protect the hive the the ant
hill or ant Hive and to protect the
queen similarly among bees and and
hornets Etc I am sure there is similar
Behavior also uh worker bees drones Etc
they some of in some species they they
exhibit some such
Tendencies then when it comes to uh
animals like the
octopus so when an octopus lays eggs it
it stops eating and it simply its entire
Duty once it has laid the eggs is to
protect protect those eggs in certain
species of
octopus and they stop eating they stop
doing anything for themselves and they
just watch over the eggs until the eggs
eggs hatch and then they die so that is
the kind of biological evolution it is
that the your purpose your sole purpose
is to eat and grow and get large toward
a certain sty certain size attain
maturity
maturity uh mate reproduce lay your eggs
and watch over those eggs until they
hatch and then you then you die and then
the same process continues over again in
the next generation of octopi so that is
what you have in octopuses or octopi and
then there is the uh what else do we
have I think there was this this myth
that Lemmings commit suicide you know Le
the Lemmings are Lemmings are a
species of of rodent that is found in
the far Northern regions in in in the
Arctic Circle and so on so these rodents
they migrate in large numbers and
sometimes they end up in the wrong place
and they can fall off Hills so it it
looks like and because there is this
herd Behavior sheep like Behavior they
don't see what's far away they just see
what the the guy in front of you is
doing that's why if they is falling off
the cliff cliff and everyone's pressing
from behind you end up falling off a CP
Cliff so they don't do do this
intentionally but sometimes it's it's
been seen to happen apparently that
Lemmings in large Quant in large numbers
fall off a cliff and fall into the ocean
or or fall a large from a large height
and most of them die so but it's not
it's not a suicidal Behavior it's it's
just something that that happens by
accident then you have a certain aquatic
animals like uh like like dolphins like
like poises like like whales
cians that beach themselves now beaching
is not understood very well why do
certain whales why do certain Dolphins
Etc Beach themselves so these animals
whales and and dolphins these are
actually animals they're not fish they
have lungs they breathe like us they
have to rise to the surface every so
often take a deep breath of air and then
go and do whatever business they they
they they conduct under the water
surface but they have to rise up
periodically to breathe so if one of
these animals gets becomes
beached on a beach away from the water
it won't lead to their death immediately
because they have lungs and they can
just survive out of the water but what
happens is that their skin it once it
comes in in in contact with the with the
air for an extended period of time and
when there's sunlight it kind of dries
out very rapidly and then that causes
their their terrible slow death that's
what that what happens and in the case
of large wave veils if you are Beach
then their Mass their body mass is so
large that it eventually you know
squashes their organs in their lungs in
the diet terrible death so I'm not sure
if it is very well understood why these
animals sometimes Beach themselves in
very large numbers maybe it is just
accidental something that happens
accidentally maybe they're migrating and
maybe they come too close to the shore
and then there's a tide whatever not
sure what happens but it is you could
say it is suicidal Behavior because it
ends it ends in the deaths so yeah there
are many examples of animals that do
exhib exhibit such Tendencies and
behaviors in the case of insects Etc it
is an altruistic suicide they give up
their lives in order to safeguard The
Hive or the community and especially the
queen in octopuses it's about passing
you know ensuring the survival of your
of your offspring of your descendants
you know spreading of your genes and in
the case of whales Etc it's not
understood why they Beach themselves but
yeah there are like like I just say
there are multiple examples of such
Behavior okay RK Paar says how would the
world change if open AI or Google
created AGI artificial general
intelligence today making them more
powerful than governments what would be
the impact on Industries the economy and
Society well if let's say a company a
private company
is able to to create AGI artificial
general intelligence which means they
have an AI system that actually becomes
self-conscious not even let's not even
self-aware but it can essentially do
everything a human being can do but much
better at a larger scale that's
artificial general intelligence so it
can understand the spoken word it can
understand music it can understand
everything we can understand but at a
higher level that's artificial general
intelligence and it does not necessarily
have to be self-aware so what happens if
this is created what happens if Google
creates or or openi creates this that
would definitely make that entity that
company more powerful than governments
obviously it's not really the power of a
government because that company doesn't
have nuclear weapons it doesn't have an
army to unleash on anybody it doesn't
have an army of bureaucrats and police
at their backend call it doesn't have
any of that but it has the AGI that can
be tremendously insanely powerful in the
right or the wrong hands so what happens
if if this scenario unfolds I'll tell
you what
happens uh first of all the moment this
happens the government the parent
government which is the US will
essentially take over this thing we will
not know that they've taken over first
of all they will not announce this to to
the public
this is not supposed to be announced to
the public because that Godlike
capability could be
secret and then they will take
full you they make make full use of that
in
uh in extending the amount of their
power so it would be the government and
the military that actually acquires the
technology keeps it secret and leverages
it to the fullest of of its potential
that's what it do and of course that
would lead to a complete American
dominance if you don't already have it
it will it would lead to the dominance
complete dominance of that country on
all the industries of the entire global
economy and the global Society so it
will be a tremendous you see technology
is a false Force
multiplier the the First Technology was
the stick and the stone so if you could
punch somebody a stick would impart way
more power than that and if you could
punch someone now you could throw a
stone with the same amount of Force but
it's a harder object it can crack
someone's skull so that's a force
multiplier then you have bows and arrows
which again you can it's a force
multiplier then you have machine guns
and so on so technology is a force
multiplier and such abstract technology
like AGI is a tremendous Force
multiplier when you couple it with
robotics when you couple it with
with with smart Warfare with drones and
whatnot it makes it tremendously
powerful and when you use it for
surveillance I mean we've heard of the
prism program the that Edward Snowden
spoke about more than a decade ago
imagine what they have today but with
just the non- AGI artificial
intelligence
Technologies and with AGI it just
becomes impossible to beat once you have
it so yeah that's what it would do so it
would it would lead to the complete
monopolization of everything by The
Entity that owns it and that is not some
that is a very scary thought which means
the rest of the world now has no chance
of anything
anymore and they would obviously
actively try and prevent any other
Nation or or any other entity from
developing similar capabilities so
yeah okay a couple of questions together
so curious Prat says do you think we can
see an AI like Skynet Terminator movies
which can be a threat to us in a few
years from now as the advancements in
the sector this sector are very rapid
and the second question is I've been
watching many Sci-Fi movies with robots
such as industrial Medical military and
humanoid robots when do you think it'll
be possible for to have these types of
robots with how AI is advancing very
quickly I remember Elon Musk had
unveiled a humanoid robot back in 2022
the dangers of AI and robots are
concerning and what do you believe is
the best way to prevent such a scenario
such as Terminator what are your
thoughts on creating humanoid robots
that look identically to humans in the
future such as Sofia even though we can
tell she's a
robot okay lot of stuff to unpack but
it's about the threat the D ders of AI
when you combine that with robotics when
so when we talk about the Terminator
movie it wasn't the AI that was
dangerous it was the robots that were
dangerous and those those robots were
dangerous because they were eii equipped
robots right and obviously they could
travel through time which is like o so
that is something we don't need to worry
about that won't happen anytime soon uh
so those robots first of all we're kind
of indestructible because they have a
metal
endoskeleton right and they were
artificially intelligent which means
they were autonomous but they had a
clear sense of purpose and they were
obviously commanded and controlled by a
Central Intelligence and they were
already they were programmed with a very
clear set of
objectives so that is what made them
dangerous and obviously the real danger
was that they sought to to take over
take control of the of the of the planet
and to enslave humanity and the nuclear
war was kind of the issue right in the
The Terminator movies uh so could this
happen so look today we don't have such
Advanced robots but obviously AI uh with
a sufficiently powerful AI we could
develop robots that are that are that
capable so in recent years you see
companies like Boston Dynamics which
have been struggling for so many years
to to develop good robots nowadays they
have robots that can dance and do
acrobatics and whatnot and you have
these robot dogs that can do terrifying
things like shoot weapons people machine
guns and whatnot so we're getting there
we're getting there soon you will have
robot soldiers an army of let's say
10,000 robot soldiers and another 10,000
robot dogs imagine that bearing down on
you so no matter how Brave your soldiers
are how valorous they are how do you
beat that so yeah we are very close to
that
actually but in the in the Terminator
movie the uh the robots were controlled
by a central artificial intelligence was
it self-aware I'm sure it was self-aware
yeah it had it had become self-aware and
it had it own its own agenda it was not
controlled by any government or any
person it had its own agenda to to rid
the the planet of humans I believe that
was the agenda something like that so
right now we are not in that scenario
where an artificial intelligence as far
as we know has has become self-aware and
has uh Gone Rogue so to
say
um so yeah
so right now the AIS that we know of are
controlled by other corporations or
governments and those
corporations um they are in the control
of the governments so that's where we
are right now uh robots so yeah that
that's all of that Elon Musk had unve a
human robot yeah sure Boston Dynamics
has unveiled really capable robots now
about Sophia I'm not sure what the
Sophia thing is I think it's a robot
that was unveiled in Hong Kong or
something which looks kind of humanlike
but you can tell that it's it's a robar
because it's still
not well it's still quite apparent but
eventually we will have humanoid more
and more humanoid robots that look more
and more like humans but the real deal
is is when it becomes Terminator like
which means you have living tissue
over uh a metallic or an artificial
endoskeleton that's when you won't be
able to distinguish between humans and
robots if that ever happens um so yeah
all so that could be further away
obviously grafting living Tissue human
looking tissue on a robot that is right
now it's completely science fiction we
are nowhere close to that if such
technology existed it would be used for
you know regenerating people's Limbs and
all that or some people need face face
transplants you could do that with their
own DNA so that it's a natural looking
face and and so on so we are still very
far away from those
Technologies but yeah Ai and Robotics
the combination is scary it's super
scary in AI the way it's progressing
yeah you could have very powerful very
dangerous robots very soon the only
thing is that AI as far as we know as
far as we are aware isn't self-aware and
it doesn't have an agenda of its own so
it all depends on the agenda of the
controlling entity which is either the
corporation or the government and we're
talking about the US mainly and also CH
the Chinese also have their own AI
systems apparently and so on yeah so
yeah that's
what let's take a few more questions
herel Agarwal says why are oceans why
Oceans Deep inside are cold but as we go
deeper in land it becomes hot that's a
great question now why don't why don't
teachers allow kids to ask such
questions it's a very fundamental
question looks very simple but it's a
great
question right so let's say you are on
the surface of the ocean in a boat let's
say at the equator at the equator at the
Equator the if you put your fingers in
the water if if you dip your feet in the
water it's going to be warm water nice
and warm okay at the equator but let's
say you you go you dive under the water
with equipment obviously the deeper you
dive the colder the water
gets you go a kilometer down it's going
to be much colder going you go even way
further down it's going to get colder
and colder of course there's something
there's there's a a limit at to which it
can become cold but the main thing is as
you go deeper inside under the ocean it
gets cold ER and there's something
called the thermocline and so on and
we'll not talk about that so that is
what we know as you go deeper under the
ocean under the water it gets colder
even in Lakes even in Lakes but as you
go deeper underground it gets warmer and
hotter and hotter why is it
so
so it all depends on what is the source
of the
heat what's the source of of heat when
it comes to oceans and lakes then what's
the source of heat when it comes to
Going Underground big difference there
when it comes to Oceans the source of
heat is the sunlight the
sun okay so the maximum sunlight is at
the equator which is which is why oceans
are really warm at the equator you go to
the polar regions there is much less
sunlight there which is why oceans are
cold and you also have icebergs and
whatnot as you go in the Arctic Circle
and all that okay so the of warmth of
heat for oceans for water is sunlight
there is no other source of heat and
obviously you have glacial melt water
you have water that continually melts
from the polar regions and some of it
reforms also and all of that is is it it
is it obviously becomes part of the
ocean and the colder the water is the
the deeper the heavier it is which means
it it will be found below a certain
depth in the ocean so that's why because
of the various regions and because of
the only source of heat being the
sunlight that's and we have night also
in the oceans so that's why you have
ocean currents and all that and that's
why you have the the phenomenon that the
deeper you go the colder it gets okay
now when it comes to the
land the deeper you go underground the
hotter it gets why is that it's because
underground you have heat what is that
heat it is the leftover heat of the
formation of the solar system
and at the core of the Earth the planet
there is the core there's an inner core
and outer core the inner core is solid
nickel iron it's believed in the outer
core is is molten nickel iron that
generates the magnetic field of the
earth which keeps us alive and then if
you go further beyond that you have
magma the magma layer and so on so forth
okay I'll you can you can look up an
image Google image of the cross-section
of the earth so as you go to deeper
underground you have all of this and
that's why you have heat the closer you
get to the magma layer and all that and
there's another source of heat as well
underground which is radioactivity
radioactive decay decay of various
radioactive elements and isotopes that
are found naturally in the earth's soil
so that also contributes to the he to
the heat of the earth and the deeper you
go the more radioactive DK cumulatively
makes its presence felt so you have all
of these
radioactive uh the Radioactive element
plus the heat from the magma layer in
the core of the Earth all of
that it causes this phenomen that the
deeper you go under the surface of the
Earth the hotter it gets so that's why
you have this tremendous disparity the
deeper you go under the water surface
the colder it gets but over here on land
the deeper you go under the land surface
the hotter it gets that is what
hopefully
explains this
matter okay next question
question Endra Endra says you said jet
engine development is very complicated
because you said we need to develop jet
blades from single Crystal yep but we
have rocket technology in ISRO and in
NASA and in the Chinese Pro space
program and the French and so on we have
rocked
technology I think high temperature
resistant materials are used in Rockets
yes they are so why can't drdo or
whichever organization it Tak is use
this same technology in jet
engines it's a great question it's a
great
question and to understand why it
doesn't work and why it's it's not that
easy you don't understand the difference
between a jet engine and the rocket
engine so in a jet engine you have this
continuous environment where all the
engine parts like the turbine blades the
single Crystal turbine blades they are
subjected to extremely high temperatures
for
extended periods of time so the
temperature can be around 2,000 de C
okay so you have this constant exposure
so you let's say you
have let's talk about a standard
airliner okay you're traveling from
let's say you're traveling from Delhi
to to London okay you want to deposit
some money in in a bank account in
London so you have a 8 Hour let's say
flight so for 8 hours you have this
airliner and that those turbines will
keep on running those jet engines will
be on in on full operation for 8 hours
and the temperatures could be 1500 2,000
de so there is constant exposure for a
sustained amount of time sustained
amount of time hours and hours to
extremely high temperature gases and
this material these the the jet engine
material uh the cover the turbine blades
Etc especially the turbine blades this
thin turbine blades they must maintain
their mechanical properties over long
period of time at high temperatures and
it's not just these eight hours you're
going to use it over and over again
right so it must be able to withstand
this for so long and yeah it's called
thermal cycling thermal cycling so that
is what a jet engine must be able to
withstand now let's talk about a rocket
engine the rocket engine it faces very
different conditions it actually faces
higher temperatures okay the the
combustion chamber in a in a cryogenic
engine or whichever rocket engine it can
reach temperatures about 3,000 degrees
and the pressures are even higher in
rocket engines extremely high pressures
but here's the difference a rocket
engine operates for short short duration
okay a few minutes uh so when it comes
to jet engines we talk about about hours
when it comes to a rocket engine a few
minutes at best 10 15 minutes okay so
there is that and uh so when it comes to
Rocket engines they they must be able to
withstand thermal shocks very rapid
Heating and Cooling during because when
you have a cryogenic engine we're
talking about very cold temperatures and
then it suddenly heats up to
ridiculously high temperatures so that's
what it should be able to withstand
thermal shock a jet engine doesn't have
to go through that so uh the rocket
engines use use various high temperature
resistant Alloys
of various various Metals I don't
remember rium niobium whatever it was uh
to do that but jet
engines can be extremely heavy I'm sorry
rocket engines can be very large and
they can be significantly heavy you can
I'm talking about hundreds of
kilograms jet engines have to be light
so you can see that a jet engine is very
different from a rocket engine a jet
engine has to operate repeatedly for
hours and hours at a time a rocket
engine typically is disposable typically
you operated once until until SpaceX
came into the picture rocket engines
were disposable you you use a rocket
engine once for about a few minutes then
you dump it and it's the end of the
story you don't have to reuse it and
Rocket engines can be much larger and
much heavier and jet turbine blades are
are thin thin and actually fragile so
you can see how different it is you can
create a gigantic big robust massive
heavy rocket engine with a tremendous
amount of thrust it'll do the job but
when it comes to jet engines they have
to be
lightweight they have these very fragile
components the turbine blades which have
to be able to withstand tremendously
high temperatures 1500 2,000 degrees
Celsius for hours at a time sometimes 20
hours at a time and it goes on forever
missions that last I mean every other
day you to go and do this so it's a very
different thing and that's why it is so
complicated and that's why the
technology that you have in ISRO or Dro
which is used in rocket engines simply
cannot be transposed and used in jet
engines very different set of conditions
that these two beasts have to withstand
very different
so that's why it's not that easy right
you got
it okay let's take a few more questions
I'm sure I've crossed 10 by now okay
balam Putin says that hypothetically if
we put the entire universe in a large
container what would be outside the
container I heard in some videos some
scientists said the human brain can only
imagine things that exist in the
universe we don't know about that but if
that is true is it possible that there
are imaginary things or creatures
somewhere in the universe
well that is speculation I don't know
but the question is the first question
is if we put the entire universe okay
I'm holding this here's the universe I'm
holding it okay I take this universe and
I put it in a large container let's say
it's a it's a box so I take this
universe and I put this universe in a
box in this container and the question
is what will be outside the container
well I'll tell you what it'll be me
outside the container what
it look we can only speculate maybe
there is the bulk of the brain world I
mean in brain World cosmology there's a
bulk outside the brain world the the
universe is is part of a brain world and
the Brain world is a three three it's a
three brain in a maybe five dimensional
or or 10 dimensional or 11
dimensional uh bulk so maybe that's
what's outside the universe and maybe
you're putting this threedimensional
brain inside a four-dimensional
hyperspace which is part of an 11
dimensional which is embedded in an even
dimensional 11 dimensional even larger
dimensional hyperspace we don't know we
can only speculate that's what I mean
but if I'm putting the universe in a box
then outside that box there is me and
whatever else is out there so that's
what I can say look this is all
speculative because we don't know what's
outside the universe we don't even know
if all of these things are true we can
only rely on the data observational data
empirical evidence that we have at hand
and that doesn't tell us anything of
what maybe Beyond even the observable
universe the actual universe may be even
larger than it actually most likely is
way way way larger than the observable
universe so what's beyond we don't know
we can only speculate and when when you
speculate it's no longer science it's
philosophy or religion or
whatever uh so yeah there you have it
and the some scientists apparently said
that the human brain can only imagine
things that exist in the
universe well I guess the universe is so
large and so vast and so mysterious and
so complex that anything you can imagine
with your brain which is part of the
universe maybe it exists somewhere in
the universe perhaps speculation pure
speculation but
yeah
okay hin says what's anti-gravity can it
somehow exist so it is it is again
science fiction there is absolutely no
evidence of anything called anti-gravity
so like you have anti particles that
have the opposite uh quantum numbers and
Quantum properties and opposite charges
Etc as particles similarly anti-gravity
could be a repulsive force similar to
gravity but have we ever observed it we
have
not so can it exist I perhaps possibly
but have we observed observed it we have
never observed it so anti-gravity is
this hypothetical force fifth force or
whatever that could have the opposite
effect of gravity so if something Falls
if you have Antigravity it actually
falls upwards or something like that but
yeah there's no evidence for
that Amit Singh says I've always
wondered what space how space looks does
it look exactly the same as images
released by NASA or will it look
different if we see a nebula with the
naked eye look
space space def dep the way space looks
it depends on how you're looking at what
lens you're using to look at it
uh if you see NASA images of space let's
say you looking at NASA images of a
space walk American astronauts in orbit
around the Earth they're doing a space
walk out of the International Space
Station if you look at let's put up some
images right I have not put a single
image on screen today so let's let's do
that give me a second and we're g we're
going to take a look at this okay uh yes
ISS sorry okay space one
so let's take a look at a space walk
image so you can see the curvature of
the Earth in these images
right so you can see the Earth curved so
this is one way of one representation of
half space looks now
in zoo space walk then okay whatever the
spelling is if you look at Chinese
images look at the Earth it is
completely
flat do you look at do you see this
there's hardly any curvature visible
here here so what is the deal it depends
on which lens you
use uh over here I'm not sure if this is
the Chinese thing but yeah over here it
looks curved but in most other images
the earth looks entirely completely flat
I mean look at how flat it looks in this
image so it doesn't mean that the Earth
is flat by the way it just means that
they use a specific kind of
lens
um uh and and when it comes to lenses it
all depends on the focal length and so
on and so forth uh when when you
use when you use what are the anamorphic
lenses and fish High lenses everything
looks really curved and the focal length
also matters and so on so that is one
example of how space looks differently
depending on which kind of camera you
use and we also have these lenses over
here you know in our eyes they also
affects the way we look at things what's
the focal length about 50 is it 35 mm 50
mm 80 mm of the human eye I think it's
35 or 50 or something somewhere in that
range so we we see the world in a
certain way which depends on entirely on
the way our eyes are constructed so you
use different cameras it it's going to
look differently but we're talking about
the Earth from space over here what does
space look like from space space looks
Inky dark just dark black from the Earth
when we look into space we are looking
at space through the
atmosphere and that's why it has
atmospheric effect Stars seem to twinkle
you go out there into orbit Earth orbit
the Stars won't twinkle at all they're
just dots bright dots in space and space
itself is just ink black that's how it
looks and it looks way larger than what
we can imagine you go out into space
it's all around you and you you're going
to be shocked at the immensity of space
it's really scary that's what I hear I
haven't been to space by the way so I
can't tell I'm only giving you
secondhand information from what I've
heard and read the astronauts
saying so yeah that's what space looks
like all right I've taken a whole bunch
of questions now let me take some
questions from the live chat I'm going
to take a few questions from the live
chat and that will be
it adya Kumar sh says Flat Earth has got
evidence yes the Chinese have have
proven the Flat Earth is right they've
produced pictures of the earth which is
entirely flat
outstanding
ah anur says 35 mm for human eyes yes
yes that's right okay if if there are
any questions I'll take a few questions
from the live chat so that there is some
interactivity um what do we have what do
we
have om Kar says what do you think about
the possibility of antimatter propulsion
for future space travel and what kind of
restrictions does it currently face well
currently antimatter is about a few
trillion dollars per gram okay there's
only less than a gram of antimatter ever
produced in various colliders like the
large hadon collider and so on
tremendously expensive to make and very
small quantities exist in the future if
we have reasonably good amounts of
antimatter great fuel for future space
travel great fuel for energy
generation okay but right now the
constraint we face is that the
technologies that we have are very very
primitive and rudimentary so the
Restriction that we Face the constraint
we face is that our technology which
produces antimatter is
extraordinarily expensive the large
hyron collider you know the energy
budget is that of a small country per
year and then only even after that much
energy cons consuming that that much
energy it produces a fraction of a gram
antimatter per per
year so that is why antimatter is is I
don't know hundreds of trillions of
dollars perram that's the the main
constraint and restriction it's
ridiculously expensive to to create and
even with all that money spent we can
create only a little much little bit of
it in the future if we if and when the
technology advances then antimatter will
be a brilliant fuel for future space
travel and also for future energy
generation
okay mu M madridista says what are God
particles and why are they so important
to understand please explain in simple
words it's not God particles it's a God
Particle and it's not really the God
particle it was not made by any God that
we know of okay it's called the God
particle I think it's the it's
journalists and the media that have
given this name to the higs Bon the higs
bon in the higs field so in Quantum
field Theory it's all field the entire
universe is just fields and the
particles are merely local excitations
in these fields so the entire world that
we see is just Maya it's illusion it's
just fields and the interaction of the
various fields that produce the the
world that we live in now what is the
higs field the higs boson the higs boson
is the particle that is associated with
the higs field and it is the particle
that endows other particles and other
yeah other particles with
mass so whichever Fields interact with
the higs field let's the proton field
interacts with the higs field which that
that is what gives the proton its mass
the electron field interacts much more
weakly with the higs field than the
proton field which is why the electrons
have much smaller mass than protons the
neutron field interacts with the higs
field approximately at the same strength
that the proton field does which is why
neutrons and protons have approximately
very similar masses and some particles
some Fields don't interact with the hgs
field at all which is why those
particles associated with those fields
have no
Mass okay so that's why that that's kind
of how I can explain this in simple
words the higs particle the higs Bon and
the higs field are
what endows the universe with mass but
some particles and Fields and their
Associated Fields don't interact with
the higs field which is why those are
massless okay and that is what these
journalists ET have called the God
particle it's the last part last major
fundamental particle to be to be
discovered it was discovered a few years
ago and that's the one good thing the
large hyron coll collider has
produced thr mudgil says thoughts on
Terrence Howard he a great actor I
believe he was part of a Nobel Prize I'm
sorry Oscar winning movie Crash or
something which was a very boring movie
from my perspective I saw it when I was
there in the
US uh yeah so good actor for sure uh
he's recently made some very interesting
statements I hear I haven't seen The Joe
Rogan EP podcast episode in which he
appeared he apparently says one time one
is not one it's two or something look
it's fine I think it's a good thing I'm
sure I'm sure what the statements he has
made are ridiculous from a scientific
perspective but he's not a scientist and
what he has
achieved either knowingly or unknowingly
is that he's brought a lot of interest
among the common people when it comes to
science they are now interested in
science that's good so Kos to Terrence
Howard I have absolutely nothing against
him and I have no issue with whatever he
has said he's not a scientist so you
don't have to take it seriously compared
to if a scientist were to make such
statements like 1 * 1 is three or
whatever so yeah he's done wittingly or
unwittingly a great job in popularizing
science and
bringing bringing people towards science
Making people interested in science so
good job sir good
job okay let's take maybe one or two
more
questions uh ram ram mahato says R Khan
Academy is is an educational platform I
haven't used it so I don't know but I
hear it's good people say it's great
Salman Khan right the guy I hear it's
great I haven't us it myself so I can't
break it personally but probably very
good
okay dend ragav says do we have any
gravitational anomalies discovered on
Earth just like seen in the movie
Interstellar um what was that anomaly
they were talking about
some yeah I don't I don't know what it
was the the guy the the the the hero he
falls into a black hole ginor or
something no Gargantua and it is a
tesseract which is a four-dimensional
thing and he somehow reconnects with his
daughter on Earth yeah that that did not
make sense before that it was all it was
all good but it's a great movie great
movie now I don't know I could not
understand the nature of the
gravitational anomaly so I don't know
what it was what is the physics behind
it okay I mean when I say I I could not
understand what it was I mean I couldn't
understand the physics behind that
gravitational anomal it doesn't work
that way that's not how gravitation
works so yeah answer is we don't have
any such anomalies that we know of on
earth like in that movie
right all right ask me questions about
science and physics not about
geopolitics here
please okay let's take one or two more
questions him says are we made of
particles or waves we are made of both
wave particle
duality phon is a particle as well as a
wave when it comes to the photoelectric
effect you can explain that effect only
by considering the particle nature of
photons when it comes to other effects
polarization Etc you would think of
light as a wave
similarly all particles are fields or
waves okay they they're part of fields
and particles are local excitations
localized excitations of those fields so
waves in those
fields so we made of both we're made of
particles as well as waves and particles
are waves and waves are particles that's
how the quantum World Works which may
not be intuitively understandable but it
is what it
is
okay liberal Mongol says can you
describe the the structure of the photon
that's a good question and I can't I
cannot
so yeah that that's that's a good
question and that's how you stump a
physicist what's a photon it's a wave
right okay let's take it as a wave first
so it's a wave it with a certain
wavelength
um yeah so it's a wave it's an
excitation in the electromagnetic field
the electromagnetic field is a
three-dimensional field which
permeates all space the entire universe
there's only one field across the entire
universe it's here also and a photon is
a local excitation in that field okay so
it has a certain frequency certain
wavelength and it is localized but it
travels at the speed of light and it has
it's made up of these transverse waves
the
magnetic uh transfers transverse Fields
magnetic field and electric field that
are at 90 degrees from each other and so
on so that's kind of what a photon is
that's what an electromagnetic wave is
like and it's also a wave packet from
the quantum mechanical perspective which
means it is a bunch of waves super
superposed on each other and localized
in one place that's the structure of a
photon and can you take a photon and
compress it in a certain region well
that's a very interesting thought
experiment but there you have
it uh yeah a good question I like such
questions
okay Muir madridista says if light has
no mass then how does how does the
gravity of black holes affect it it's
not just the gravity of black holes that
affects light it's also the gravity of
stars effect affects light when you have
a solar eclipse then you can see star
light from behind the sun visible so the
light the path of the light is curved
how does it happen it's because the
presence of mass curves SpaceTime and
makes the light travel in curved lines
instead of straight
lines that's how it
works okay some more rapid fire
questions
Cricket come on
have you watched The Big Band Theory I
haven't watched The Big Band Theory but
I watched a few episod of Big Bang
Theory it was very funny in the
beginning uh exaggerated versions of
physicists it was funny in the beginning
yes angat Singh OB says why are space
agencies pursuing a nuclear po power
spacecraft well it's one way of doing
space travel it can help you reach Mars
let's say very rapidly and it can help
you transport a tremendous amount of
bulk to large distances let's say you
want to send 1,000 tons into space to
Mar well if you want to do that then you
can use a nuclear powered spacecraft and
use thermonuclear explosions to start
the process
yeah
right
um what else Bobby Bobby says have you
figured out new types of Battery
Technology what kind of techn what what
kinds of batteries do we have we have a
lithium ion batteries right well you
could even have sodium ion batteries or
some other ionic batteries I'm sure so
there are other types of batteries that
can be made and sodium is a very readily
available substance as you know it's one
of the most abundant substances in the
world
go to the Sea you have sodium chloride
salt all over the
place and you can yeah you can get
sodium from that and sodium ion
batteries can be made but obviously
sodium is a is a very it's a very no
what's the term it's it's very highly
reactive sodium so we we get complaints
of of lithium ion batteries Catching
Fire when well imagine what sodium would
do but I'm sure you could mitigate this
I'm sure you can find a way around this
so one of the
potential uh Battery Tech technologies
that can be explored is sodium ion
batteries Krishna anger says
microplastics
unavoidable maybe maybe there's just so
much plastic out there now waste plastic
in the oceans and other places that
microplastics are just all over the
place and the future Generations will
have to somehow deal with this we
finding microplastics in the blood of
people we're finding microplastics in
various organs in people and so on is
not good is not good but that's what we
have done to ourselves to to our
environment so there's micro
microplastics everywhere in intact water
in ocean water so on so kind of
unavoidable now and we don't know what
the long-term effects are going to be
like but yes yes that's that's what we
have himank says how does gravity react
when we reach absolutes zero no change
no difference the temperature makes no
difference on gravity gravity is gravity
yeah so when it comes to the cature of
space time it doesn't matter whether a
black hole is cold or hot it's going to
have the same effect on the curvature of
space time so
yeah absolute first of all you can't
really reach absolute zero uh
hypothetically theoretically you can but
yeah we have never seen anything at
Absolute Zero but even if you do it will
make no change on on the way that
substance or that mass uh affects
gravity or it's or its gravitational
field all right what are your thoughts
on vasuki indicas says arou so they've
discovered a new snake fossilized snake
dating back that was alive a few million
years in the Indian
subcontinent and apparently it's as big
as or if or or maybe larger than the
Titanoboa snake that used to live
somewhere in Africa a few million years
ago so this snake is now has been given
the name vasuki indicas so I say great
great we had gigantic snakes in the
subcontinent millions of years before
Humanity existed interesting so I'd like
to see a maybe a Bollywood movie with
that snake being
resurrected like you know that you have
movies about the Megalodon the Meg and
all that let's have a Bollywood movie
with vasuki indicas coming back to
life all right
um Bobby Bobby says it's literally okay
you're talking about uh microplastics
yes it's everywhere the bottom of the
ocean in organs we humans have to leave
a big footprint that's what we've done
uh and we're still doing that you know
there are lots of countries including
our own country where there's a lot of
trash plastic trash plastic waste being
thrown out without being recycled and
all it all all goes out in the oceans
China is doing it there are these
gigantic patches in the ocean in the
Pacific Ocean Etc these giant patches
where it's just plastic plastic plastic
for hundreds I don't know tens of square
kilometers and all that and that plastic
eventually breaks down not chemically
but physically it becomes microplastic
and then it goes everywhere so yeah yep
plastic is everywhere I don't I don't
see any solution to that right
now okay
lots of questions let's take two more
questions him okay himang is asking lots
of questions uh what if we could
transfer our Consciousness into an AI
model what makes us human is it our
Consciousness or our
body look we don't have any definition
of
Consciousness science doesn't have a
definition of Consciousness let's say I
have a black box H we talk about the
black box thing right let's say a black
box how do I
know if there is the Consciousness
inside that black box or not which means
I will have to force I have to force
myself to Define what it means for a
system to be conscious how do I Define
it I don't have an definition physics
doesn't have a definition information
Theory doesn't have a
definition biology Neuroscience
chemistry we don't have a definition of
Consciousness in any of these
disciplines so we know Consciousness
exists when we see something we know no
whether it's conscious or not it's like
life when we see something we know it's
if it's living or not I have these books
behind me I all of us know the moment we
look these are not living beings these
are not living organisms right and when
we see something that's alive even if
it's a flower if it's if it's a plant or
a shrub we know it's alive we can
instantly recognize that this being is
alive it's like the same thing with
Consciousness when we see it we know it
you see a cat I know it's conscious I
see a B I know it's conscious at a
certain level even plants are aware of
their or of their environment so we know
it's there we know it exists but we
don't know how to define it so if we
can't Define it how do we transfer it
somewhere right because to First
transfer it I need to have it somewhere
in some data set or something or this
data set then how do I transfer it
intact so you know it's not possible
right now with current technology or
with the current understanding that we
have we which is that we don't have any
understanding of what it is right so
what makes us human consciousness or
body it's Consciousness that makes us
human our Consciousness is different
from the consciousness of a bat or a dog
or a bear or a rhinoceros or a cat or a
bee it's the Consciousness that makes
different that makes us different but
what is consciousness we don't know we
don't know what it
is okay
okay all right I guess that should be it
for today I know we have a 100 more
questions
um can humans see UV rays we can't
because the the equipment in our eyes
the the retina the the rods and cones
Etc uh don't react I mean they
don't they don't resp respond to those
wavelengths or frequencies of flight so
that's why we don't see
it
um okay I guess we
will om beerer says can neutral stars
have habitable
planets um
look it depends on what form of life it
is the kind of form of life we have on
our planet we need sunlight to Keep Us
Alive without the sun we are dead the
sun is truly Our Father it gives us
warmth and light and from that all
energy comes in the planet I mean we eat
plants some of it us eat eat eat animals
but all of these plants and animals they
are alive because of sunlight plants do
photos synthesis through sunlight and
then animals eat plants and we eat
animals and we also eat plants and so on
so all the energy on the planet most of
it 99.9% comes from from sunlight now
neutron stars don't have that much
sunlight they're very
dim compared to a star like the Sun so
will they be able to
produce uh sustain a planet like ours
maybe if it is a different form of life
it's possible so yeah it depends on what
kind of life we're talking about we only
think of earth-based life that we are
familiar with waterbased life forms
carbon based life forms life in the
goldilock zone of a star but there could
be other forms of Light of Life so it's
possible that even neutron stars may
have habitable
planets you may even have some some
strange form of forms of life on the
surface of neutron stars themselves who
knows yeah
yeah okay gentlemen ladies uh thank you
so much for all your questions uh I
really appreciate that very interesting
questions uh and we're going to keep
doing this so every week we're going to
have one science session in which we'll
talk about physics science AI technology
all of that stuff so I'm going to end
this session today I think I've exceeded
what I had planned to do I I plan to do
take to take 10 or 15 questions from the
from the comments and some questions
from the chat but I've done more than
that so anyway I'm going to end this
session over here today thank you so
much for your questions and I will see
you in the next live stream you can
attend the geopolitics history one or
you can attend the next science one
depending on your choice thank you so
much and keep
reading about science and learning about
science and keep raising your standards
thank you so much I'll see you in the
next live stream bye-bye